<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Oh My Heart // A Blog by Alex Ezell</title><link href="http://aezell.github.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://aezell.github.com/feeds/personal.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://aezell.github.com/</id><updated>2013-03-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>I survived the StartupBus</title><link href="http://aezell.github.com//2013/03/09/startupbus-2013/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-09T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Alex Ezell</name></author><id>tag:aezell.github.com,2013-03-09:/2013/03/09/startupbus-2013/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Sunday morning, our &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt; texted me and told me to read my email. I swear he&amp;#8217;s only done that like two times. The last time, the site was down for a week. So, yeah, I&amp;#8217;m going to read that&amp;nbsp;email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out that our Director of Business Development had been talking to a fellow named Ravi Singh at Spring Marketplace. Ravi was headed to Nashville on a bus full of hopeful entrepreneurs and I was being given the opportunity to get on the&amp;nbsp;bus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;StartupBus began as a joke/bet between an Australian named Elias Bizannes and some friends. Three weeks after making the joke, he had 25 people on a bus headed to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SXSW&lt;/span&gt; with the goal of building a company in three days, $500 in his pocket, and a bill in his hands for&amp;nbsp;$20,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four years later, there were six buses with this same goal. Hailing from San Francisco, Chicago, Tampa, two from New York, and even one from Mexico City, these buspreneurs were set to build real businesses and pitch them along the way. Each bus has a pair of conductors who are StartupBus alumni who guide the teams and also make sure we all get where we are&amp;nbsp;going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined the Portioned team whose goal was to build an app that could grab any recipe on the Net, parse out the ingredients necessary, let you adjust servings to your needs, and then send that as an order to Peapod, FreshDirect or the like for&amp;nbsp;delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the bus hurtled toward New Orleans, I got to know the team and settled in working with some Elance freelancers to get a logo made. Then, I helped hone a press release, with some of Suzanne&amp;#8217;s help. I was also helping write some Javascript code along the&amp;nbsp;way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time we got to New Orleans, we&amp;#8217;d already inked a possible partnership with a store in Austin called in.gredients that is a no-waste, no-packaging food store. We spent the night in New Orleans in a hostel that was a former orphanage. It was a unique experience and certainly forced some bonding for all of&amp;nbsp;us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day we headed to San Antonio and along the way were practicing our pitch to the whole bus, writing code, writing press releases, and doing lots of other things you&amp;#8217;d want to do to get a company off the ground in three days. We were greeted in San Antonio by lots of &amp;#8220;rackers&amp;#8221; (people who work at Rackspace). They rolled out the red carpet for us and it was a great&amp;nbsp;welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few hours later, we pitched to Elias and a few other StartupBus conductors. It was the first time I had done anything like this and I was very nervous. I felt good about our idea, but we hadn&amp;#8217;t really built much of the site yet and there were bugs galore. The demo was harrowing but we&amp;nbsp;survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;29 teams or so pitched at this level and only 12 would move on to the semifinals. My team made the cut and sat down quickly to hone the pitch based on feedback. We still had a few bugs to figure out and a few features to try to complete. We also tried to hone the story to get to the value of the business as quickly as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The semifinals came quickly and our pitch was pretty good but we didn&amp;#8217;t make the cut to the finals. At this point (Wed. evening), I&amp;#8217;d had a total of about 10 hours of sleep and totally crashed that night in the hotel. On Thursday, the six finalists made their pitch in San Antonio and two were chosen for the All-Star&amp;nbsp;Finals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These All-Star Finals were comprised of the two teams from the standard competition, two teams who had traffic and other engagements online, and two teams from the Alumni bus along with a few teams chosen for special consideration by the bus&amp;nbsp;conductors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That All-Star Final was held last night at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SXSW&lt;/span&gt; here at Austin at an event sponsored by Rackspace. The winner was a team called CareerMob whose application will help guide veterans just getting out of their service into the skills they&amp;#8217;ll need for the careers they&amp;nbsp;want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been an amazing experience for me. I&amp;#8217;ve learned a lot about how teams can work together, how businesses come to life or die quickly, and I&amp;#8217;ve learned a bit about how much sleep I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s honestly just now sinking in about what StartupBus has meant. It&amp;#8217;s a powerful, transformative experience that I am very grateful to have&amp;nbsp;had.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="startup"></category><category term="entrepreneur"></category><category term="startupbus"></category></entry><entry><title>How I lost 100 pounds in six months</title><link href="http://aezell.github.com//2013/01/08/100-pounds/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Alex Ezell</name></author><id>tag:aezell.github.com,2013-01-08:/2013/01/08/100-pounds/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year in early June, I was applying for life insurance. Of course, they do a lot of blood tests and they weigh and measure you and probably probe into your medical records. Turns out, I was too fat for life insurance. On June 16, I weighed 340 pounds. I&amp;#8217;m 6&amp;#8216;2&amp;#8221; which means by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BMI&lt;/span&gt; was 43.6 which put me well into morbidly obese&amp;nbsp;territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my being overweight, I found out during the life insurance tests that all of my blood levels were fine but one: liver enzymes. Turns out I had fatty liver syndrome from the large amount of belly fat I had been carrying around for more than a decade. Men are especially susceptible to this because we carry so much of our weight in our abdomen. This leads to fat being deposited inside the liver where it limits the liver&amp;#8217;s ability to do its&amp;nbsp;job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of people, I had long thought about getting more active and eating better. This life insurance problem was the push that I really needed. Turns out that it coincided with a positive shift in my spiritual and emotional life that started back in January of&amp;nbsp;2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, as I write, I weigh 236 pounds and my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BMI&lt;/span&gt; is around 30.4. I feel immeasurably better and can do things I thought impossible months ago. I exercise joyfully on a regular basis. I made it through the holidays eating all the wonderful treats my wife made and didn&amp;#8217;t gain weight. I&amp;#8217;ve learned a moderation and planning with regards to eating that I never knew before. So, how did that&amp;nbsp;happen?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tracking and&amp;nbsp;Accountability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I&amp;#8217;m a nerd, I of course turned to technology to help me with my&amp;nbsp;goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started tracking my food with pictures and text on &lt;a href="http://aezell.tumblr.com/"&gt;a Tumblr blog&lt;/a&gt;. I was also documenting my workouts&amp;nbsp;there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a month after I started, a coworker suggested I try out the &lt;a href="http://www.loseit.com"&gt;LoseIt! site and app&lt;/a&gt;. That made all the difference. The iPhone app lets me search for calorie and nutrient content for lots of food and can scan barcodes for food purchased in a store. It can also track calories burned from lots of different kinds of&amp;nbsp;exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also purchased a &lt;a href="http://withings.com/en/wirelessscale"&gt;Withings scale&lt;/a&gt; which wirelessly sends my weight, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BMI&lt;/span&gt;, and fat percentage to the LoseIt! app each time I step on&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep myself accountable, I set up LoseIt! to update Facebook every time I worked out and whenever I weighed it would update with the amount gained or lost. Knowing that others can see your progress or lack thereof is a powerful motivator. There&amp;#8217;s also no discounting have friends and family cheer you&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LoseIt! has tons of nice features. I especially appreciate the graphs and weekly email&amp;nbsp;reports. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a graph of my weight loss for the last six months. It shows a nice drop and smoothing out over the last&amp;nbsp;month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Weight Loss Graph" src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0J2L2K2I350W371m3c1a/Screen%20Shot%202013-01-08%20at%202.22.32%20PM.png" title="Weight Loss Graph" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I focused on removing fats and carbs from my diets. I dropped the fried foods, the bread, the sweets, the sugary drinks all of that. I focused on lean protein and vegetables as much as I&amp;nbsp;could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app started me out on a program with a certain calorie budget for each day. Exercise adds to the budget while food subtracts from that budget. My daily average of calorie intake for the last six months has been around 1200 calories. It has increased as I&amp;#8217;ve gotten more fit and exercised more and my metabolism has increased. The app does a pretty good job of letting you manage or manipulate the budget to fit your&amp;nbsp;needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this lower caloric intake, I&amp;#8217;ve learned to listen to my body better. I now know when I am full and when I&amp;#8217;m actually hungry. I used to just eat as much as I had on my plate whenever it was time to eat. Now, I eat for fuel. I still enjoy treats and special meals from time to time. It&amp;#8217;s actually more special and enjoyable&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This graph shows the percentage of my calories coming from fats (blue), carbohydrates (gold), and proteins (green). One thing to point out is that I try as much as possible to have the carbs be complex carbs and not things like refined sugar. Still, when the wife makes a homemade &amp;#8220;tres leches&amp;#8221; cake, I&amp;#8217;m going to eat&amp;nbsp;some.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Macronutrients Graph" src="http://f.cl.ly/items/3Q1o1S2C2F1b0w2W0H2j/Screen%20Shot%202013-01-08%20at%202.34.52%20PM.png" title="Macronutrients Graph" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One tool I&amp;#8217;ve used to get some good protein into my diet are protein or nutrition bars. I especially like the &amp;#8220;Pure Protein&amp;#8221; brand. These have carbs too, but they are limited and they can provide vitamins and minerals that might otherwise be lacking if you are limiting calories. Just be sure to read the labels carefully to be sure of what you are getting. Some protein bars are little better than candy&amp;nbsp;bars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For workouts, I started with the elliptical and walking on a treadmill. I could only do about 12 minutes on the elliptical on its easiest setting and could only walk for about 20 minutes. But I kept doing&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a graph of my exercise calories by month for the last six months. Interestingly, I exercise more and harder now than I did in August, but I burn less calories. As you might imagine, moving a 340-pound body takes a lot more effort than moving a 240-pound body, so even a little less exercise back then meant more&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Exercise Calories Graph" src="http://f.cl.ly/items/38210O2I3E2l2u2d3v1M/Screen%20Shot%202013-01-08%20at%202.26.02%20PM.png" title="Exercise Calories Graph" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I reached about 280 pounds, I felt fit enough to try running. Given my size and history of knee issues, I was worried about injury so I wanted some guidance and pacing. I chose the &lt;a href="http://www.active.com/mobile/c25k"&gt;Couch-to-5k app&lt;/a&gt; from Active.com. It walks you through 3 runs a week progressing in length and difficulty. Primarily, it uses interval training with walking interspersed with jogging. On about week 7 of the program. I had to backtrack a couple of times because I didn&amp;#8217;t feel ready to move on or went too long between&amp;nbsp;runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found myself doing the elliptical about 3 or 4 times a week at the beginning. When I started adding in the running, it moved to 2 or 3 times a week with running being 2 or 3 times a week. I did occasionally mix in some light weights, but found I wasn&amp;#8217;t seeing much benefit because I wasn&amp;#8217;t doing it often&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Couch-to-5k app pushes me as it should and I do try to run a little farther and faster with each run. On the elliptical, I&amp;#8217;ve continually increased my speed and the resistance the machine uses, but I never really do it for more than 45 minutes at a time. In my research, working past that time frame has diminishing returns for weight loss. It can improve your performance or endurance but those weren&amp;#8217;t my goals starting&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to weights, I recently bought Mark Rippetoe&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Starting-Strength-3rd-Mark-Rippetoe/dp/0982522738"&gt;Starting Strength&lt;/a&gt; and plan to start a strength program in addition to elliptical/running. It professes a simple program of barbell exercises to gain strength and mass. No fancy machines or crazy exercises. Just four or five movements with impeccable form. We&amp;#8217;ll see how it goes for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#8217;t talk too much about finding the motivation for exercise. That differs for everyone. For me, the nudge provided by the life insurance debacle was enough to overcome a lifetime of being fat. It helps that I&amp;#8217;m vain enough to want to be able to wear normal clothes. You&amp;#8217;ll need to find that thing that gets you up at 4:30am in the cold and dark rain to get to the gym or to put on your running&amp;nbsp;shoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached my goal of 100 pounds on Dec. 21 (appropriately, the supposed last day of Earth). Since then, I&amp;#8217;ve focused on maintaining my loss and pushing my exercise to new levels. Even through the holidays, through discipline and moderation, I saw no weight gain despite enjoying my fair share of cakes and sausage dips and the&amp;nbsp;like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has become a new way of life for me. It&amp;#8217;s not a diet I&amp;#8217;m doing or a exercise plan. These things have just become a part of the way I&amp;nbsp;live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through a combination of carefully tracking my caloric intake and macronutrient balance while continually pushing myself harder and farther with exercise, I&amp;#8217;ve been able to steadily decrease my weight, gain more energy, sleep better and wear clothes not bought in the big and tall section. As the saying goes, if I can do this, so can&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="health"></category><category term="weight loss"></category><category term="diet"></category><category term="exercise"></category></entry><entry><title>Dependence and Independence</title><link href="http://aezell.github.com//2012/10/12/dependence-and-independence/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Alex Ezell</name></author><id>tag:aezell.github.com,2012-10-12:/2012/10/12/dependence-and-independence/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was talking with some friends about the nature of dependence the other night. I made the comment that there was a point in my life where I probably didn&amp;#8217;t understand what it felt like to be completely dependent on another&amp;nbsp;person/thing/organization/whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;#8217;m sitting on my couch as my son is sleeping. He&amp;#8217;s been sick today and is generally just feeling puny. I&amp;#8217;m looking at him now and thinking about this notion of dependence and how he is completely dependent on me. It&amp;#8217;s the basic core responsibility that every parent faces. Yet, to him, it&amp;#8217;s just the way things are. He doesn&amp;#8217;t know that there&amp;#8217;s a way to live where he doesn&amp;#8217;t need to be dependent on&amp;nbsp;anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That sounds like it should be something to strive for. That we should all strive to be independent. We are often encouraged to be this way in our school years. In fact, our son is at a Montessori school where independent work and thought is highly&amp;nbsp;important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, there&amp;#8217;s an aspect of our lives where independence has few, if any, benefits. That&amp;#8217;s in the realm of the spiritual. That is, in the way we deal with other human beings and how we move through the world making contact with other people, it may well prove beneficial to rely on people. If one is so inclined, it may be even more solid to rely on one&amp;#8217;s definition of a higher&amp;nbsp;power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My son could almost certainly wake up right now and even though he&amp;#8217;s only 3 years old, go upstairs, wash his face and hands, change clothes, and eat a little something to see if he feels better. That would be a strong, independent series of actions. I would be proud of him for doing all those things without&amp;nbsp;assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when it comes to the times when he&amp;#8217;ll have to face real struggle small or large, like a friend being mean to him or a grandparent passing away, he&amp;#8217;ll need something more than a basic set of instructions or list of tasks. He&amp;#8217;ll need to rely on those around him that love him and if he so chooses in the future, his own definition of a higher&amp;nbsp;power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found, in a relatively brief period of time, that my own independent spirit has been borne of dependence on close friends and my conception of a higher power. It seems that by shuffling off to those I rely on the small slights and perceived wrongs that the world foists on me each day, I am able to spend time and effort on the deeper, core challenges of being a kind, loving, tolerant person. That&amp;#8217;s got be a good place to spend my&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s not to say that I unload all my crap on others and let them deal with it. It has become the sort of thing that deep friendships do best. I complain or grumble and my friend provides levity and objective perspectives that inevitably allow me to see a clearer path unclouded by my ego and self-serving instincts. In turn, I must do the same for them, or else I&amp;#8217;m simply back to the state I described in the opening. Sure, I&amp;#8217;d be dependent on someone, but if I can&amp;#8217;t be dependable then it all falls&amp;nbsp;down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It nearly goes without saying that I am not in this enlightened state all of the time, or even a quarter of the time, but it&amp;#8217;s a state to which I strive and an effort I&amp;nbsp;enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="kids"></category><category term="responsibility"></category><category term="dependence"></category><category term="spirituality"></category></entry></feed>